πr^2 gives you the area of a circle
but where does πr^2 come from ?
first, we'll
draw circle and fill in it's area
next we will divide it into large equal parts and arrange them in a rectangular
formation
as you can see it barely resembles a
rectangle
so next we will divide the circle into
small equal pieces
and we will arrange them in the same
manner
you can see that it appears more like a
rectangle
so if we divide the circle into
even more smaller pieces
you can see that every time the shape
becomes more like a rectangle
so how small must we divide a circle
before we can get a perfect
rectangle?
well, we can keep on dividing the circle
into small, smaller,
or the smallest pieces you can make
but the answer is to divide the circle
infinitely many times until we cannot
distinguish the lines
and eventually the circle
can now become a perfect rectangle
so the area of the circle is equal to
the area of the rectangle which is equal
to base times height
the height of the rectangle
as you can see is the same as the radius
so height is equal to radius
to find the base
we need to look at the circumference of
the circle
and when we compared the base and the
circumference we can see that the base is
equal to
one-half the circumference
remember that the circumference is equal
to 2πr
when we combine it with one-half
the two's cancel out
and base is equal to πr
so now base times height becomes πr times r
combine the r's together and we have
πr^2
which is equal to the area of the rectangle
which is equal to the area of the circle
so πr^2 can be used to calculate the area of any size circle
that exists